It's high noon in old Cheyenne. I'd like
to call the March 17th, 2026 meeting of
the finance committee to order. Ask if
you're in the room that you silence your
cell phones. Uh making public comment
clearly identify yourself when making
public comment online. Use the raised
hand function. in person approach the
podium and please turn on the microphone
and there will be no additional business
discussed after the completion of this
agenda. All communications go through
the chair and with that miss uh clerk
give us the first item please. Number
12, ordinance third reading, repealing
the ordinance number 463,
which specified the monthly storm water
runoff management system user fee in
accordance with section 13.32.050
of the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming.
Do we have a staff report?
>> Madam, chief of staff,
>> chair, through you, Amber Ash, chief of
staff for the city of Cheyenne. Um,
before you for consideration is the
repeal of the storm water user fees on
third and final reading. Um, this is
pursuant to conversations with the
legislature. um an agreement that the
administration would act in good faith
um with the legislature to identify and
work on alternative options to resolve
our storm water runoff needs.
>> Any questions from the committee to the
chief of staff?
Not seeing any. We'll go to public
comment.
Labour. Welcome.
Uh, thank you, chairman.
I uh
want to comment on this most unusual and
I think ill advised action.
It is uh as I'm sure you're all aware,
we spent over a year, a lot of money,
and really did quite a bit of outreach
to communicate the dangers that we face
from storm water runoff.
And while I recognize what happened at
the legislature,
I wonder if that's adequate. I wonder if
this is really uh going to be the end
here where there's an interim study of
many water related issues. This is
certainly not the only water related
issue in the select committee. Um and
certainly probably it's a
probably some information come out of
it. But I want to emphasize uh Mr.
chairman,
the uh period of time that we're living
in,
I want to emphasize that today about
half of Nebraska is on fire.
The East Coast is being racked by
tornadoes.
We just had a totally unprecedented
uh do
storm that caused damage to a lot of uh
people and businesses and trees around
here.
And yet um we can't seem to get it
together to do much about storm water
management.
And I would suggest to you uh members of
the committee and to the public or any
of the staff that
it's really essential that we don't just
wait
and hope that the legislature is going
to find a way to assist
and they will have to assist
all the municipalities in Wyoming with
storm water management.
I don't think you can say Cheyenne is uh
that important. Certainly, we know that
the other communities that have these uh
programs in place are going to continue.
They're relatively minor. Laramie
repealed theirs. But I hope I'm making
my point here, Mr. Chairman.
Uh summer's coming.
Uh
we all
know that
the storms are much much worse.
But I would suggest that we should be
looking at going to the absolute worst
danger spots in our drainage system
and doing what we can to relieve them.
And I would particularly point out the
uh
choke channel between Ridge Road and
College Drive along Dry Creek.
Um it's
uh not only uh
a wellrecoognized problem. We did do
some drainage uh work cleaning just up
the
road from it that cost a fair amount of
money and hopefully helped. But have to
remember that the entire
massive system that we now have out
there that comes from the Kerry
reservoir and that major channel under
Converse and over to uh Ridge
empties right into that area.
So it's a choke point. And I would
suggest to you that if we're going to be
serious about this, we can't just repeal
and hope.
Uh we really need to take a look at some
of those choke points and we really need
to do what was obvious to me. Um, I'm
sorry we didn't do more and better
communication about this
because there might be individuals that
think they can file a lawsuit and
intimidate us
uh stop us from following our long
planned and very important program.
But I would suggest to you that that
might not be a good idea period.
uh those that don't like an ordinance
that directly directly speaks to health
and safety that we worked long and hard
on. Well, hey, we'll just sue the city
and that'll take care of it. So, um I
recognize that uh nothing's probably
going to come out of committee here
except a recommendation, but I do want
to note
where we live, what we live with,
and the fact that um
in my opinion, we should really at least
at at this particular moment
when this repeal is obviously going to
pass.
Come up with some answers to what we can
do
now and here.
And
um
I'm sorry, Mr. Chairman. I just have uh
real concern with the Wyoming
legislature at the present moment and
the way they're operating.
So, um thank you for your time. Uh I'm
sorry that this is happening.
But it's one of the challenges I think
we have to face. And when we do that, at
least we need to be able to tell our
constituents,
business people,
children, the community that we're not
just throwing up our hands. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Councilman.
Any further public comment in the room?
Any public comment online?
Can we get a motion?
>> Mr. Chairman, I'm I move to approve on
third and final reading.
Thank you. Sorry to my colleagues. Not
sure what happened. I will second that.
>> It's been moved by Moody, seconded by
White. Any further comments or
questions?
>> I have some.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you.
Um, as stated two weeks ago during the
our last finance committee. This did
pass in December of 2024 before I was
sworn in January of 2025.
And as I said, then I would have been a
no vote. I think it should be up to the
voters. But for the public and my
colleagues, if you Google Cheyenne
stormwater, click on the uh first link
and scroll down to the bottom of the
page and to the RGIS map, click on some
of the larger industrial buildings here
in town. Some of those monthly fees
would have been Union Pacific $18,433
the refinery $7,750
the Microsoft data center of Christensen
$5,050
the Lowe's distribution center $8,800
Magpool Factory $1,75
some small businesses $33 to $50
you know and I'll say it again how can
we save our business friendly. When
these are the monthly fees, they're
pretty high. You know, I'll keep saying
if it was a flat fee of $3 to5
for everybody, both commercial and
residential, $36 to $60 a year, that
would probably be supported by our
constituents.
I do think the storm water
infrastructure needs to be funded by
increased future proportion fifth penny
or uh andor six penny you know let's use
some of our reserves that are needed for
some of the storm water infrastructure
like the dried creek put off some of the
beautifification aspects temporarily
that are expensive because I know it's
expensive to do storm water fees let's
get back to the basics that's what our
constituents demand they want. They went
to the respective state legislators, not
only here, but in Albany County, because
they were frustrated. They felt like
their voices were not heard when this
was implemented. And this repeal was
really constituent driven. Yes, help the
legislature, but really go boils down to
our constituents. And you know, I know
we hear about the weather that and I can
say this is somebody that has a master's
degree in geography, somebody that has
close to two decades in geography.
Yes, there's some, you know, climate
change, whether human or, you know,
driven naturally. However, there's going
to be a lot of weather patterns. This
year is an anomaly. It was like that
back in the 1930s during the Dust Bowl
and actually a lot of the patterns are
fitting the 1930s. So, that does change
from time to time and I can say somebody
who is has that experience of two
decades in this field. So, as a
geographer, we do look at the climate
aspects too. So that's all I have. Thank
you, Mr. Chairman.
>> Hey, uh do you have any comments to
make, Councilman White?
>> I do, Mr. Chair. Um I'm very uh sorry
that uh we're at this point today. um
knowing uh all the hard work that staff
and uh council representatives both past
and present worked on this
and um
you know I think our staff worked really
hard to try to develop a formula uh that
was as fair as possible. It was it was
based on um how much square footage of
property uh one owned uh which is what
determined the fee. Um none of us were
exempt. Um I have a kind of a smaller
home but a bigger lot and so I I
certainly was going to be paying into
this as well. But it was something that
I was certainly uh from a personal
standpoint happy to invest in be just
because I know of the need um just
because I have friends in North Dakota
who suffered greatly when the uh Sue
River flooded uh several years ago. Um
it's um it's difficult and uh it's it's
it's disappointing that the legislature
forced our hand here, but they did. And
um so I hope we get some direction and
some uh leadership from them since they
have chosen to uh have this as an
interim study. Uh and hopefully they
will have some good recommendations that
comes out of that study and that we can
all move forward regarding this. uh
because
um you know, one comment that my
colleague just made that I will agree
with is that it does need to happen in
some form. And so uh um
that said, I'll be supporting the repeal
today based on uh all the future uh past
information and comments that have been
made.
>> Well, thank you. We'll probably have to
take a multiaceted approach to this, but
u all those in favor signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Post. No.
And that that motion is unanimous. The
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to approve at the next meeting
of the governing body. Next item,
please.
>> Number 23. Resolution authorizing the
city of Cheyenne to approve and submit
the Wyoming Division of Victim Services
funding application for fiscal years
2027 and 2028.
>> Staff report, please.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Julie Anthony,
victim assistance coordinator for the
Cheyenne Police Department. Uh through
you, sir.
Can you hear me? Okay, sir. It's the
goal of the Cheyenne Police Department
victim assistance program to provide
services that facilitate the physical
and emotional recovery of victims of
crime in our community. Victim
assistance advocates provide
trauma-informed services to victims of
crime and those services include ongoing
case management, connection to community
resources such as housing, mental health
counseling, crime victim compensation,
social support services, and child care
resources.
We also provide individualized safety
planning, direct victims to medical
care, accompany victims to medical
appointments and medical forensic exams,
and provide onseen support for victims
in crisis.
The rapid support model our department
utilizes is crucial for victims of crime
as rapid advocacy support of victims
lessens the likelihood that they'll
experience severe long-term mental
health concerns as a result of their
victimization.
Advocates are often the first line of
defense in identifying suicidality and
providing intervention and mental health
support.
Rapid advocacy support allows victims to
access urgent financial assistance that
forestalls long-term ramifications such
as eviction, job loss, and aggravated
health concerns due to lack of financial
access to medical care. Ongoing case
management gives victims of crime one
consistent point of contact within the
police department or handling their
cases. and that avoids confusion and
allows information to be made more
readily available to both victims of
crime and investigating officers.
During the previous 2-year grant cycle,
Cheyenne Police Department victim
assistance provided 1,486
victims of crime with 1,918
instances of service.
196 instances of unseen crisis response
or crisis intervention were also
provided.
Victim assistance services are crucial
for the support and recovery of crime
victims in the city of Cheyenne. State
division of victim services funding
assists in these efforts and it is for
this reason that I respectfully request
that the city council approve this
resolution.
I thank you for your time and
consideration and I'm happy to answer
any questions you may have.
>> Thank you. Uh any questions for Miss
Anthony from the committee?
>> Well, thank you.
>> Go to public comment in the room.
>> Seeing none, do we have any public
comment online?
Can I get a motion? Uh, Mr. Chairman, I
move to adopt.
Second.
>> It's been moved by Councilman Moody,
second by Councilman Lion. Any further
comments or questions?
>> Uh, Mr. Chair, I'd just like to thank
Julie and her staff. Um they really they
really do important work in our
community and as you heard uh the
statistics that Julie mentioned um
really really unbelievable that the
numbers that high over the course of a
year but uh thank goodness for them and
thank goodness for uh the important work
that they do. Happy to support this.
>> Thank you. All those in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Any opposed? Seeing none, the
recommendation from the finance
committee at the next meeting of the
governing body will be to adopt. Next
item, please.
>> Contract modification number one to
contract number 8267
between the city of Cheyenne and plan
one architects for the municipal
building renovation design project from
general fund reserves.
staff report.
>> Adele Bartell, public works staff
engineer.
Um, with this contract modification, we
will be requesting $439,550
for the renovation design of the old
senior center and $427,500
for the renovation design of the
municipal court's second floor for a
total of $867,050.
Um, our goal is to um have these two
facilities renovated before this
building so that we can use them as
temporary office locations for staff
during the renovation of this building
and also as a permanent location of the
um city council.
I'll be happy to take any questions.
>> I'll answer questions for our staff.
>> Council McMoody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Threeu. Uh,
thank you, ma'am. Um, from this contract
I looked at total is uh $2,341,600.
So the uh public knows how much have we
paid out from this contract so far?
Hey, Mr. Chair, through you. Uh, we've
paid 165,000 so far.
>> All right. Thank you. Follow, Mr.
Chairman.
>> Go ahead.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Chairman, through
you. So, just scenario, if the six penny
fails for the renovation,
um, will we be on hook for this whole
contract?
Mr. Chu, yes, we would. Um, but we would
at least have the plans for the future
if we ever
>> Thank you,
>> Councilman White. Do you have any
questions?
>> Um, just one comment, Mr. chair and that
is I think it's wise that we proceed
with this just just um if the six penny
does pass uh to have a backup plan in
place for relocation of employees I
think is is smart. I know that when the
Hler building was renovated several
years ago, um there was this mad rush
for commercial space all around town and
it was uh pretty chaotic for state
employees at that time. So, uh the fact
that we're um recognizing that and and
having a backup plan regarding
relocation of workers if the project
moves forward, I think is a is a smart
plan. So,
>> right. Thank you. We'll go to public
comment in the room.
Councilman Labour.
Uh thank you, Mr. Chairman. Um
this is a very interesting uh
change of events in a series of actions
that seems to bring together
some extremely important
issues here in this building and with
our staff.
I'm uh not sure that uh
and I heard comments uh just a few
moments ago about the um what if the
sixth penny doesn't pass.
I
uh certainly hope that and I expect to
work towards the fact that this sixth
penny in this particular
ballot is critical to us just as uh the
public safety center was and um really
it's the the mechanism that we've used
for things like this.
But I'm wondering and I hope maybe I can
get some information here before Monday
night
regarding how this is going to play out
with the reserves. I mean, is this the
idea that we have sufficient reserves to
pay for this design and the construction
of this the rehabilitation of this
building?
Um, that's uh something I certainly need
to know and I think I think that we need
to really look at uh how we uh talk
about and work towards
uh this very important matter. I I
there's just no question that that space
down at the uh
courthouse uh can be rehabilitated and
used effectively
uh not only in this
immediate future but in long term
and certainly I agree that uh the
former cafeteria and uh area there of uh
Burke high-rise is would be a great
recycling and use and I certainly um uh
looking at those at least preliminary
schematics seems sensible to me
but uh I just can't see us uh pressing
ahead with this without a better
explanation
of what might happen and what uh
should happen and how it happens.
because this is a very challenging time
and I don't uh
believe that the amount of money uh
currently on the ballot is going to be
sufficient.
I'd sure like to know about that
because I believe the ballot's been set
and how we handle this is uh going to
have an impact in that in that in the
voters. I think when we look at uh are
you going to proceed with this plan,
I think that it's necessary,
but uh
it doesn't seem to me to be as
thoughtful as it needs to be in this
time of great uncertainty. Thank you.
>> Any further public comment through
>> um Mr. Mr. Chair, I have one more
comment to make.
>> Okay.
>> Um just as a reminder, the voters had
approved the $2.5 million to design this
building um on the 2021 ballot. So um
they did want this at some point.
>> Okay. Council Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I was have a
point information. So just for
clarification if it was approved by a
six penny shouldn't this be coming out
of the six penny earmarked and not
general reserves
>> Mr. share through you. Um
so our funding for that um 2021 six
penny was specifically for this building
and the design for this building and we
are currently um there is currently
$94,771
left in that fund and we're planning to
use that for a CM and um construction
for this building.
and answer your question since they're
talking about the other building.
>> Just a followup question, Mr. Chairman,
if I can
>> go ahead.
>> I guess so. Did the ballot say for
construction or just for design plans? I
mean, I I don't have the ballot in front
of me. Does anybody anybody can answer
that?
>> I could try. Craig Lavoy public works.
Yes, that 2.5 million was for the design
of the city municipal building. And
since we've started that project, the
other two projects that have came up was
the senior center and the desire to re
um to finish the design of the municipal
court building. Those were not on there.
So therefore, the design has to come
from general fund reserves. The the
voters did not
have a choice to approve that. It wasn't
on the ballot.
Thank you. My questions are answered,
Mr. Chairman.
>> Okay. Council White, do you have any?
>> No, Mr. Chair, not at this time.
>> Do we have any public comment on my
saying? None. Can I get a motion?
>> I'll motion for the sake of discussion.
>> I'll second.
>> Okay. It's been moved by Councilman
Moody, seconded by Councilman White. Uh,
any further discussion?
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through
you, uh, thank you for those comments
and information. It was very helpful.
Um, I'm going to be a no vote just
because the voters when they approved
it, it was for the building, not the
other ones. We have a responsibility to
our constituents and what they want,
what they don't want. I do think this
$800,000 could be better spent on some
of the storm water mitigation. And I
also think it's kind of putting the cart
before the horse. We don't know what
they're going to decide on municipal
building with the sixth penny. Okay? We
don't know whether they want it or they
don't want it. So that's why I think
we're getting a little too premature
with this. If this was say in October,
be a different story. Say, "Yep, the
voters approved of it. You know, let's
do it." Or, "No, they didn't. So it's
not even before us." So, I think we're
getting a little ahead of ourselves. And
again, the building design plans that
was it was a six penny one that'd be
different, but this is general reserves.
I can't do that this time. Thank you,
Mr. Chairman.
>> Councilman White, you got any comments?
>> I do. And uh but you know, I kind of
understand where my colleague is coming
from. However, um I do think that once
that uh ballot measure is voted upon uh
then if it is approved, then we really
need to be ready to go. And so
um you know, this is a use of reserve
money. Uh we've been very fiscally
responsible to build up our reserves so
that we're in a position to uh have
this. And as Adele mentioned previously,
if it is if it does fail, then we still
have the plans in place for the future.
Um the second floor of the municipal
court building was always planned at
some point to be built out and finished
uh for some use by city staff. Uh so I I
don't have a heartburn with that. Uh the
senior center uh building is something
that just presented itself to us once
their ballot measure was approved and
they were able to build a new facility.
Um so I don't really have any heartburn
with that either. To me it's a it's a
great use and a great location of space
and a good deal for the city to occupy
that building in in some capacity. So
I'll be a yes vote today.
also having uh toured it and uh sitting
through the work sessions on these uh
feel that it's a necessary step forward
for the city to be making at this point.
So all in favor signify by saying I
>> I
no
>> no.
>> Uh the chair will vote I to break a tie.
Uh the recommendation of the finance
committee will be to approve at the next
meeting of the governing body. Seeing
that's our last item, we are a journ.